Hello, welcome. It is June 11th, 2025.
It is active inference guest stream
lucky number 111.1.
Uh, very nice. And we are with Jorgi
Gorgiv who will be presenting and then
we'll have a discussion on modeling and
predicting self-organization in dynamic
systems out of thermodynamic equilibrium
part one attractor mechanism and power
law scaling.
We will look forward to a presentation
and some Q&A. So if you're watching live
feel free to ask a question. Thank you
for joining Geri to you.
All right. Thank you Daniel for inviting
me. It's my great pleasure to talk to
like the active inference institute
audience and uh hopefully we have um a
lot of um interests in common so we
could u have a good discussion or
continue to explore those questions. Um
I personally know some of the people in
your group so I hope uh we'll find a lot
of commonalities.
Um yes as you said um I'll be talking
about some of our recent work on um
computer simulations with uh modeling
and predicting self-organization
in dynamical systems and what we think
is driving the self-organization.
what is the basic mechanism that's uh
leads to increase of order in those
systems and how the different
characteristics
um relate during the process of the
self-organization how they grow together
and I'll show a lot of examples from
other areas to connect to like why is
this important why is it interesting
and um on this title slide I put the the
big picture the arrow of time as
presented. This was a poster made by
Eric Shaison when he was at um Tufts
University at the right center of
science education. Uh we were like next
uh his office was uh next door to mine.
So we had a lot of great conversations
and we found that we're interested in
the same questions. And actually I had
the exact same like conical view of the
expanding
future and the arrow of time as leading
to more interesting things, more
organized systems, more intelligent
systems and uh needless to say I was
very pleasantly surprised when he made
this uh poster. So
this represents the arrow of time from
the big bang pretty much capturing
uh everything from the pure energy
through formation of structure in uh
particles in formation of atoms of
galaxies of stars, planets, chemistry,
biology,
cultural evolution and whatever comes in
the future.
And
the big uh in many people's minds it has
been ingrained that the second law of
thermodynamics is predicting that
everything is uh going to a state of uh
thermodynamic equilibrium to entropy and
that's why a lot of people are very
pessimistic about the heat death of the
universe.
But meanwhile a lot of interesting
things are happening which go in the
opposite direction. they're becoming
less and less
um those systems are becoming le in in
less and less of equilibrium. They
they're moving further away from
equilibrium.
And the interesting question is why does
this happen?
Why they don't just disintegrate? Why
they don't fall apart? Why does this why
this process of increasing of complexity
and structure and everything that we see
around us has not stopped
let's say a random number of billion
years ago if it ever started
and why why do we observe everything
around us right now how did it come to
be well I guess that's a question that a
lot of people are thinking from
different angles and have different
answers
and Um
I want to point also to another aspect.
Not only that the process of
self-organization in the universe in all
kinds of different systems is moving in
an arrow of time of increasing
structure, increasing complexity further
away from equilibrium.
But it happens at an accelerated rate.
It has been happening since the big bang
and it doesn't seem to be slowing down.
If anything, uh I know that some of your
audience who told me from machine
learning and AI, boy, that's an
acceleration.
Every day there are new things. So, uh
and that's a great example of
self-organization when you put tons of
information in a neural network and it
finds a pattern and you don't know what
happened. It it happened by itself, I
guess, as far as I know. Maybe the other
uh it's it's not my area of of expertise
but what I have heard is there is a a
kind of structure formation in that
information space. Uh so this is another
this called a cosmic calendar and it's
also well known since probably the 70s.
It was made by Carl Sean and I was
fascinated by these topics when I was
watching it in the 80s in Bulgaria
where I was born and uh I couldn't wait
for the next episode where he was
explaining exactly this interdisiplinary
connections between different areas of
life of science of culture of history of
physics of astronomy and putting it all
together and uh his cosmic calendar
represents that u let's let's look every
so the universe roughly 15 billion years
old he mapped it on a year which is 12
months every month is about a billion
years a little more and from the big
bang which is January the first billion
years February March
not much is happening now we think with
the new observ observations. There could
be some more interesting things. But in
general, when we look back, we see
majority like very small galaxies, small
small clusters. In the Milky Way,
our own galaxy forms about in May, which
is 5 billion years later. Not much
interesting things happen, at least from
our point of view, until the solar
system forms, which is in September of
that year. And then quickly
photosynthesis emerges in October, in
November the ukarotic cells. And now for
December, we need this whole panel
because things start to accelerate
enormously. We have the like fish on the
17th of December, land plants, insects,
reptiles, dinosaurs, mammals on the 26th
and pangia splits on 27th. So you see
that on this cosmic calendar
pretty much the human history
the first ape divergence is on December
31st on the last day in the humans the
homo erectus the anatomically modern
humans like 11 neanderals diode 11:59
p.m. And in the very last minute of this
enormous span of time uh the last few
seconds we have the
agriculture like 202 seconds before
midnight and third cities and China and
uh Christ was born like 4 and a half
seconds before midnight and Columbus
came to America like 1 second ago. So it
seems like there is some driving force
that's not only pushing the universe
towards creating
order and more interesting and more
sophisticated systems. But it's doing it
in exponentially or super exponential
acceleration
rate which as you could see here like
the the difference in increase of
complexity in this last few seconds like
I mean since Columbus came here we are
now at that AI and super intelligence
like that the acceleration is
fascinatingly
um robust. fast and not only robust but
it's getting faster and better. So why
is that? Why? First question is why
order in uh is created and increases at
all and not only that why does it happen
faster and faster? Why doesn't it go
constant rate? And there is uh just to
confirm this um cosmic calendar
acceleration. There is uh this is from
Ray Kurszswwell. He compiled uh data
from Carl Sean and uh all these other
sources here, the American Museum of
Natural History and Cyclopedia
Britannica about major transitions in
kind of cosmic complexity, new
structures like plants, animals,
uh why uh like um civilization and
before that more chemistry and and atoms
emerging.
and how long before the present day they
happened.
So on the y-axis you you see the time to
the next event how many years you have
to wait. So pretty much at the beginning
you have to wait like 10 billion uh
years and when you approach the present
this is 10 here on the x-axis time
before the present this like 10 years
before now pretty much you see that uh
those events are happening closer and
closer together and all these sources
pretty much uh line up on the same kind
of trend and you
people have objected they say oh how did
you choose these events but there are
there are like transitions in complexity
there are like major milestones and
that's what people are looking at and
that's why he compiled all these sources
to minimize the error so again
tremendous acceleration and complexity
transitions as we are approaching the
present
and um going back to Eric son he defined
a metric which is called free energy
rate density.
It's it has some caveats but in general
his idea is
uh the amount of energy flowing through
this um complex self organized systems
um per unit mass. So that's why it's in
units of energy per second per gram. So
it's like the flow the energy rate
density through the systems and uh again
on the x-axis you have the time before
present and uh you could see the
enormous acceleration in the you could
say that the free energy rate uh through
the system is a measure of distance from
thermodynamic equilibrium. Right? like a
jar of gas if you leave it in the
kitchen or or the temperature in your
room is pretty much at equilibrium.
Every point has the same temperature.
But in those systems, you have great
differences inside them in all kinds of
measures, not just temperature. And that
distance from equilibrium is correlated
with the structure of those systems like
stars, planets, animals, brains,
society, etc.
And um Ray Kurszswwell looked at uh
calculations per second. That's why he
was able to do all these accurate
predictions of um computing in computing
technology and AI where he actually
mapped that on a super exponential like
the his his points for uh comput
calculations per second per thousand
versus time and this only until 2000 but
I've seen his most recent plots until
2025 they are all on this white uh kind
of dashed line and um that's also
accelerating. So wherever we look we see
gigantic
rise in complexity and structure and
information and we see super exponential
acceleration
or at least like Moore's law is strictly
exponential but it's only a fraction of
this um paradigm here for the CPUs.
Obviously, Ray cursor looked further
back. But even if you took a small
portion of this data set, uh even
exponential acceleration is is very
very big deal on longtime scales as we
know. All right. So
now the question about this huge variety
of structures and this huge kind of
diversity between systems is very very
complex by itself and uh to answer it we
need to go to something simple
and uh try to understand that first and
then try to build on it and here I'm
showing an example of a system that
people have studied a lot which is
self-organization
sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp sp
spontaneous organization happening by
itself just when you pass energy through
a system and in this case on the left
you have so imagine you're sitting at
your kitchen and you have a pan with
water and you turn on the the heat and
now you have a hot bottom plate and cold
top surface in the room, right? And
honestly by eye you don't see much but
if you people put like different
particles inside to see the motion of
the fluid or we use a infrared camera we
could see the the structure formation
and what happens is a small difference
in temperature between the bottom and
the top. Obviously now the according to
the second law of thermodynamics the
heat that has to be transferred from the
hot to the cold from the bottom to the
top but at very small differences it's
enough to just that the thermal
diffusion the collisions between the
molecules are enough and the fluid stays
kind of still
the heat is transferred slowly
but if you increase the temperature on
the bottom plate then something
interesting happens that mechanism of
energy transfer is not enough and the
fluid self organizes in what's called
convection rolls. So if you look from
the top uh there will be these long um
lines which are basically the this is
looking from the side to show that the
convection pattern of this uh of the
water or oil whatever fluid you have.
And um not only that,
but if you increase this temperature
difference even more, then you could go
through a whole set of very intricate
patterns.
Uh this is uh kind of a computational
study, but in the lab we could observe
this a very simple image here of like
this will break into u sometimes a
honeycomb structure. They look like a
beehive kind of uh like where the bees
put the the honey uh six kind of angled
shapes and then if you increase the
temperature even further you get
different shapes. So basically this is
what people mean when they say self
organization I think it's more
appropriate appropriately to say energy
induced organization because the flow of
energy
it seems is the
driving force that creates structure in
those systems and again this is the very
very simplest system that's that I could
think of uh which just has the fluid and
the temperature difference and yet it
could create this variety of structures
imagine now all other kinds of a lot
more complicated systems and uh life
systems that are life and that you pass
energy through them and then you have
metabolic cycles and all other kinds of
patterns. It's just mindboggling. But
it's at this level of science, it's
almost impossible now. It's so
complicated. It's almost impossible to
understand everything. But can we still
say something meaningful?
Okay. So
we looked also at um well known to
biologist scaling laws which are that uh
if you increase the size of animals
let's say you go if you go from a mouse
to an elephant the metabolic rate
uh changes. In other words, they use
less energy per unit mass and they
become more efficient in their
metabolism.
And um
we looked at CPUs. So and also the
energy passing through the CPUs here
that x-axis is total number of quant
which means um quant means uh we are
using units of uh physical action but if
you normalize it per unit time it's just
the energy that the CPU uses and the
number of transistors inside. So as you
increase
uh the number of transistors in the
CPUs,
well you could say obviously they'll use
more energy, but we shouldn't forget
that they getting smaller and smaller
and smaller. So it's not that obvious
how much more energy they should use and
what will be the pattern. So now these
two scales are logarithmic, the X and
the Y and a straight line. you could
pass a straight line through the data
points is a power law relationship,
right? So one is the other
time uh to the power of some number. And
just to compare we looked um at uh
brains and the energy consumption of
brains again in like terms of total
number of quant that will be the power
used by brains of animals at different
size and the neuronal count in the
brains.
And I was amazed to see that like uh
they form
they much much more lined up but uh they
form the same power law relationship and
if I mean the brain is not a computer
but still there are units in the brain
and there is energy passing through the
brain and they are scaling in uh
proportional relationship. So there is
something that says some that gives us
some hint about uh underlying dynamics.
All right. So our approach so I'm coming
from physics is to go to
basic principles of physics
and um ask the question why and how
those systems self-organize and can we
measure or how can we measure this
degree of organization. And if we put
two systems next to each other, both are
complex, both are performing some
amazing things. But do we have a basis
to say which one is more organized,
better organized, which will be if you
have a biological system like which one
will out compete the other which is more
fit and there is a basic principles
principle in physics called the
principle of least action.
uh in other words uh it was said by mapu
in the 1600s that nature is most
economical in all of its actions and
before him even the ancient Greeks and
many other the dowist philosophy is also
based on this efficiency principle so it
seems like um I mean in science it's not
usually accepted to talk in terms of
final goal of kind of teology of a
system. But if a system tries to become
most economical in everything that
happens in it, it will restructure
itself, reorganize to get to even more
economical state or more efficient
state.
And in our society, we have economies of
scale, right? So if you have a bigger
plant or a bigger company, the more
units you produce of the same thing, the
cheaper they get. So you have this
size and um efficiency relationship.
Okay. So
what does this principle? So now based
on this principle, I'll show you the
mathematical
definition of it. But um just to tell
you beforehand that for those of you who
are not physicists, those of you who are
physicists, you all know that all
branches of physics everywhere in
relativity, in quantum mechanics, in
classical mechanics, in
electromagnetism, in fluid dynamics, in
optics, everything is derived on this
principle. String theory
that every textbook starts with this
principle and derives equations. So
mathematically
it looks like this. So if you
uh take two points the starting point
and the ending point
uh for travel of some in physics it will
be a atom or like molecule some particle
and uh in more complex systems. I would
like to think it should be applicable to
any motion even in biology and in social
systems because if this principle is
valid and governs all the motion in
physics why not why should stop working
all of a sudden in in those systems
which are composed by the same atoms and
molecules.
And uh it says the following that out of
the all possible trajectories or paths
that an object could take from the
starting to the ending point.
You could see some of them here
represented with like wiggly lines. It
always takes the shortest path. And this
symbol delta here means if we vary this
path we increase the what this is called
the action. I'll define it in a second.
But basically, it becomes less
efficient. The motion becomes less
efficient in terms of action. And that's
what means that nature is most
economical of in all of its actions.
Basically, it's most action efficient.
It does everything all of the motions
are happening with the least amount of
this quantity action. And uh here is how
it looks. So I here stands for action
and delta is this variation. If you vary
it make it a little bit smaller or
greater
and this integral here here means that
we just take the whole path from the
beginning to end from t1 to t2 when we
start the motion when we end. And this l
here is in physics it's simply the
difference between kinetic and potential
energy. So to give you another very
obvious example, if you take your pencil
now and you drop it in the room,
well from experience, you can predict
which way it's going to go, it's going
to fall in a straight line. And if you
calculate the action for it to move on a
straight line and to move on a curved
path to the left, to the right, to
wiggle, uh all of those other paths will
have higher action. So if you vary the
action, you always get higher values.
But if you drop it a million times, it a
million times it will fall with the
lowest action on a straight line. And
the same is true for much more
complicated systems. Um again even for
fields not just for objects. That's how
we do physics. All right.
Um now when we consider a complex system
obviously it doesn't involve a single
object and by definition
it's a collection of it's a system right
it's by definition it has a multitude of
objects or you could call them agents
that interact with each other that
travel along paths
that have to if you represent the
complex system as a network. In biology,
you could have a metabolic network. In
computer science, you could have a
neural network. Um, now how does this
minimization
could help us there if we want to apply
it, right?
And
in in expanding the definition that we
saw previous on the previous slide for a
single object here I is the same amount
the same quantity action in the integral
of the lrange and it is the kinetic
minus potential energy but now we say
this is each of the objects in the
system
uh let's say I is the number of the
object let's say you have 10
agents 10 atoms or whatever it is, they
are moving and they do J crossings
between the nodes of the system and we
sum all of these the action for all of
these crossings or all of these events
that they perform to get from A to B and
we
we say all right if each of them obeys
physics laws there is no argument to say
that they don't
then the minim minimization of the sum
of all these
actions
should be zero. So what does it mean the
sum? Why don't we say each of them
individually? Well, if we have a system
that has many crossing paths,
uh obstacles inside, right? Neither of
them could move on their own least
action path. Neither of them could move
on a straight line. They have to find
curve paths to get from one uh node to
the other, from one starting point to an
ending point.
But all everything that's happening
there, we're saying
to obey the laws of physics, it should
be minimizing the sum of these all of
these actions. And not only that as
we'll see later
uh it will be to minimize it it will be
like a temporary state but in this
cosmic evolution as you go through
different levels of uh structure
formation it should continue to
decrease. So this is called a stationary
action principle where the every
variation is greater and you find uh
some stationary value. But we want to
think in terms of evolutionary systems
of dynamical action principles and I'll
show you in a second how it looks. So
this is our starting point that we take
all of the actions for all of the agents
in the system and minimize
that that sum
and we could express this as a ratio.
um it could be derived from stochastic
dissipative action principles but for
now I'm not going to show that um so the
ratio is the following so here we have
the same thing n objects they do m
events m crossing between the nodes here
is the sum of all of the actions for all
of those crossings and here we'll
multiply some constant h which is called
the planks constant it's the smallest
unit of action in physics And we say
that this ratio we call it action
efficiency. In other words, how
efficiently the agents in the system are
moving to perform their functions.
And we say that the more action
efficient the system is
or the the larger the smaller the the
denominator, the less energy and time
they need to use to perform their
functions. That's a signature
of better structures structure in the
system shorter paths. If it's biology,
it could be enzymes that are speeding up
reactions. If it's neural networks, I
think I've seen people apply similar
principle optimization principles even
in in neural networks and economics
there is optimal control principles.
uh so they use not the same but similar
approaches.
So basically we say that the
organization in our language the
organization of the system will be
reflected in this efficiency. In other
words, if a system is more poorly
organized, if the agents have to travel
longer distances to get from here to
there, they'll perform slower their
functions. They will consume more
energy. And if you put two systems next
to each other, if they're biological,
one will out compete the other. Even if
they're in economics, one will be more
efficient, people will buy the more
efficient one. So for us, the measure of
u how well organized a system is is this
action efficiency. And here we just like
compress the notation. And we say this
total amount of action, the sum of
everything that happens in the system
over the planks constant. We call it we
label it with the symbol Q which means
this sum of all of the actions. And uh
the flow of events or the number of
events all agents times all the
crossings that they do is phi which is
flow of events.
And uh this same equation here becomes
uh the number of things that happen the
number of events functions in the system
divided by the total amount of action
expended for it. Right? So,
but if this was the only thing that
happened,
then
I would expect if the the least action
principle was the only factor that
determined how systems should
self-organize and how they should form a
structure because it acts everywhere in
all particles. there will be life on
Mars and there'll be life on Venus and
uh everything will be getting more more
complex but
in our understanding that's not the case
because the
level of structure in the systems as I
that's why I showed this previous slides
that as the size of the system is
increasing the number of components is
increasing in proportional manner
depends also on
we talked a little bit before that about
cybernetics on this positive feedback
loops between all of the characteristics
in the system. I'll give you a short
example before I go on. But let's say if
we do a simulation of ants forming a
path between the foot and the nest,
right? It could be any, you could call
it other things. But if we put very few
ants, they don't form a path. Even if
you go in the forest, you look at the
ants. If you have very if you have one
ant and it goes to the foot, it will
never form a trail, right? So you need
some critical number of agents. So that
already tells you that yes you will
minimize the action but in order it's
conditional in order to minimize it you
need some number of agents you need some
amount of energy flow through the system
you need all these other prerequisites
for that to happen.
Okay. So um SD lap so lap stands for
least action principle and SD stands for
stoastic and dissipative
um least action principle because it has
been extended for I would say already
close to a 100 years by and many others
to
uh include in this um equation for
action not just kinetic and potential
energy
but also dissipation,
also random effects.
But even with all those effects, systems
um or objects still tend to minimize
this quantity of action.
And um
all right so our basic model you could
include any number of characteristics I
just put several here
is that we understand so our so the
action efficiency will be the measure of
how structured is the system how
organized how efficient how closely it
obeys the physics laws but it does so in
conjunction
with all these other characteristics in
the system and I'll name them but before
I say that I purposely labeled alpha the
action efficiency as the quality of the
system right how efficient how well it's
performing its functions and Q like the
total amount of action in the system as
the quantity or proportional to the size
of the system
and in um philosophy in dialectical like
uh In Hegel's dialectics, the quantity
quality transition was one of the main
three main mechanisms of pretty much
progressive evolution and I think that's
absolutely
um true and and working in this uh
example. Uh so here we have
the efficiency of the system, the
quality, the quantity, the total amount
of action. N is the number of agents in
the system. Uh we saw before the number
of transistors, the number of neurons.
Five is the flow of events. Let's say if
it's a brain, how many I don't know
information, computational events, or if
it's a computer, how many calculations
per second it will do. And we say that
each of those reinforces each other. So
in other words, if I increase the size
of the system,
I'm creating more opportunities for it
to restructure itself to reorganize to
perform its u functions more
efficiently. That will increase the
quality.
But as it increases the quality, it
creates shorter paths. It consumes less
energy. then it will allow for the
system to grow so it could attract more
agents and it it could perform more
events the flow of events. Um I was
always uh giving to my students when
they start a very simple example and
I'll give it here because I know the
audience is broad but uh I'm based in uh
the Boston area and we had a big project
here which was called the big dick.
Basically, the Boston Highway was the
most congested in the country until the
'9s,
and for about 10 years, they had to
destroy the highway 93 and put another
highway underground and new branches.
But the efficiency of the transportation
right getting from one point to the
other in the city was getting so low
that the population growth of Boston
stopped. Nobody was building anything
new and even it started decreasing.
people were exiting the city and as soon
as so basically you have that if you fix
one of these quantities you arrest the
other right and as soon as people build
the infrastructure they put the new
highway then it became
uh action efficient like fast and with
less expenditure of energy to get from
point A to B and people started moving
into the city and building and the
population continued to row until it
exceeds the limits disproportionality
values between quality and quantity
basically and it will stop again and
then it will um people will find the
need to build a new infrastructure to
increase the efficiency. So I see those
as inducing each other helping each
other in this in this example. All
right. So in general,
let's say if you open a textbook on
general systems theory, let's say
Bertali, if you have several quantities
that in a positive feedback loop, they
reinforce each other, you could model
them with um just simple differential
linear differential equations where the
dot here means the time derivative, the
rate of growth of alpha, the action
efficiency, the rate of growth of Q, the
total action, the rate of growth number
of events, the rate of growth, the
number of agents in the system. Uh, and
they depend on all of the others, right?
I could increase
alpha or q or phi or n and that will
reflect the the growth of of this
quantity. And this linear system of
differential equations,
it's a very simple system. I mean it
could be made a lot more complicated
with nonlinear effects with others but
it's complicated as it is. So let's
start simple the solutions
are exponential growth.
So just if you suppose this positive
feedback loop between all of them and
you plug them into this equations and
you solve the equations each of them
alpha qi n in time it grows strictly
exponentially. So I'm like aha is there
something to do with the acceleration of
order in the universe? So there are
positive feedback loops acting in all of
these different types of systems that
make them selforganize faster and faster
like in the cosmic calendar of of Carl
Sean and in the graphs of um Ray
Kurszswwell
and Eric Sha and um
uh here I put some mathematical details
but uh if you ask me I'll go through
them but at the moment I'll skip. So
basically these are the exponential
solutions right each of them is its
initial value time exponent some number
times the time so they grow exponential
all right but when you take any uh any
of those exponential equations and you
combine them if you ask me I could go
through that and I have them in my
papers but if you combine them
algebraically you get power law
relationships between those quantities
always between alpha and ni and n and q
and I didn't show the others alpha and q
all of them right so they grow
proportional to each other with some
power and now going back to the graph
with the number of transistors in CPUs
as the uh power consumption grows that's
a power load the number of neurons in
the brain brain as the power consumption
of the brain goes power wall I'm like is
there any connection here is this
signature of this underlying dynamics of
this reinforcement between the different
characteristics of the system this
interdependent kind of mathematical
functions
and here just to show something that
everybody knows we plotted the
transistor count versus time for CPUs
which is on a low linear scale a
straight line that's the same like this
graph here low linear straight line
that's an exponential growth. So is
there something in the growth of
computing that is uh obeying these
dynamics right and um
all right so we think that
at least on the first approximation
again this model could be made with
fluctuations with noise with other terms
but it seems to be following this
predict pred predictable mathematical
pattern where you could say if those
characteristics reinforce each other
they predicted to grow exponentially
then I look at different systems
and I plot them on low linear curve they
are straight lines they grow
exponentially it predicts power law
scaling I look at brains I look at CPUs
I look at animals they have power law
scaling Jeffrey West had a book in 2007
17 called scale where it has probably
thousands of those scaling relationships
between different characteristics.
So is this a signature of some
underlying dynamic that drives the
systems forward not just describes but
pushes them to become more organized and
more sophisticated and more evolved.
Right? Cosmic evolution is the term uh
that people uh use like Eric Shaison and
Carl Sean and others and um I know the
big history community also has contacted
me because they also interested in the
same questions like this big history
from the big bank until now why are
these events happening so could this
principle help with that explanation
and AIE stands for this Average action
efficiency. Basically,
we say that we can use it to
measure the how close the agents of the
system obeying these physics laws and
also to predict or to determine which
will be if the system continues to
evolve
what will be the the most efficient
state or the most organized state of
that system. that it will eventually
reach. So we think that this shows some
promise of predictive power
of emergent structures. Right? In our I
will show our simulation, we could
predict that if we if the agents obey
the least action principle that they
will start with random state and form a
path that is a straight line if there
are no obstacles and they do.
um and also
um explanatory power as to obey this
principle of least action.
Um that's why that's why they are
self-organizing. All right. So
some examples
very few examples of size complexity
rules. It was uh named in 2002
paper I think by Bonire. Well, it has
also from 93 some data but um has a lot
of data and he compiled from different
papers. So these are uh mean techno
units per tool in
um populations in Oceanania.
uh predicting technological complexity
and the population size. I mean he would
look at Oceanania because he wants to
look at kind of isolated islands,
isolated societies otherwise you have to
consider them as a part of the bigger
system. And uh this is a logarithmic
scale. This is uh this is also
logarithmic scale. He fits the data with
a straight line which is one of those
power law equations that we show. Then a
different system number of cell types in
biological systems and the total number
of cells in those organisms very noisy
very dispersed but people have fitted
with a power law relationship right so
you have the number of cell types is
some measure of complexity right you
could create different organs different
structures and the total number of cells
is the size of the system right the
hegel's uh quantity quality transition
As you increase the quantity of the
system, its quality, its structure also
is increasing. Um, about ants, here is
number of ants in ant colony on the
x-axis lo scale in the lo number of
casts in the ant colony increasing with
a power law relationship. Here is from
uh torching the evolution of complex
hierarchical society, different
countries, population of countries
as it grows through time and
hierarchical level in those countries
like different institutions
local lock scale power law
relationships.
Um here the lock of number of
occupations in different states of India
and the population of the states of
India. The bigger the state, the more
different the larger number of different
occupations there are. Some measure of
complexity. And I just even put because
this is interesting to put together the
joint growth of population in the world
and GDP per capita. And as the size of
the world increases in terms of
population in blue, the GDP growth is
increasing par in parallel which
suggests this coupling this power uh
relationship. One is some number times
the other and also it shows this
exponential or or rather super
exponential growth. uh our model this
simple model predicts exponential which
is kind of a similar curve but
wherever we look it's it's it's amazing
it's everywhere. So we looked also at
some more kind of simple physical
systems. We
uh we looked at uh here the all right.
So we look at the different stars with
one of my previous students and he uh
measured the progress of nucleioynthesis
in those stars in terms of the size of
the stars in terms of the mass like
measure as a measure of the size of the
stars. So the bigger a star gets, the
larger fraction of its initial hydrogen
it converts to heavier nuclei. And not
only it does, it's on a lock log scale.
All of those are straight lines, but it
does so in this proportionality
relationship in power wall scaling. And
the different lines here are just
different starting initial fractions of
heavier elements. It's called
metallicity in astronomy.
And um not only that but the rate of
nucleioynthesis the in other words the
acceleration how fast they are producing
those heavier elements as you increase
the number uh the mass the number of
solar masses or the size of the star.
Not only they produce larger fraction of
their mass uh turn it into heavy
elements but they do it way faster than
the slow ones produce the small one. So
we see the power law scaling of the
progress of nuclear synthesis as a
measure of the complexity of the star in
terms of its mass and the acceleration
right the the bigger they are the faster
they do it. So
it's very exciting that no matter where
we'll look uh we see those probably one
could look for exceptions and try to
falsify it but um again there in Jeffrey
West and other books there are a lot a
lot of examples of scaling laws. All
right so let me show you one of uh what
one of my students did last summer. So
he did in agent uh agent based
simulations in net logo
um with ant colony where you have like
um the foot and the nest and here I'm
showing like the 3D version of the
simulation you could put different
obstacles you could put friction you
could make it as you could create a maze
you could make it as complicated as you
want and ask them to find the shortest
path but in the simplest case this is
just a 2D view of the simulation ation
or the version of the simulation. And
here is the world X and Y. And they
would start in green. The green ants at
the initial state there. We start them
totally random like the gas molecules in
the room. There is no structure, right?
And then they randomly pass through the
foot and the nest. They pick up a
pheromone. As they move, they drop a
little bit of it and it evaporates. It
diffuses. But if another ant senses that
it crosses the path, it starts moving
along the gradient of that pheromone.
And in the red here is some intermediate
state where they probe several different
paths. So it already looks like with the
least action principle where you have
several longer paths and now they answer
exploring them trying to figure out
which one they like and finally they
settle on the one that's closest to the
shortest neither of the long paths. They
don't like the the long action paths.
Uh, of course you have some wiggles here
because you have some memory effects
which aren't passed where but u in
general if you leave them long enough
they will uh like create shorter and
shorter path they will make this line
straighter. So basically they'll
minimize their action to cross. If you
think of a big network with millions of
nodes, this will be just two nodes of
the network and the agents in that
system when they're crossing these two
nodes out of all possible paths, they'll
choose always the shortest one. In
network theory, you have like geodasic
distance like the shortest distance as a
measure. And here's just how the
simulation would run, right? They'll
start randomly
and now they will restart again where
they disperse randomly and then uh they
will explore different paths find the
pherommones here is the intermediate
stage and finally they'll settle on the
closest path to the straight line to the
shortest. So basically here I'm
describing like what happens at each of
those steps but I already went over this
but yeah random to forming the final
trail and the least action efficiency in
the first state when they are moving
everywhere and not achieving anything
and the highest action efficiency at the
end where they're crossing for the
shortest time and with the least energy
expenditure.
And this is for those of you that are
curious how the simulation window looks
like. You could change,
you could put as many parameters as you
want. You could change them. You could
ask all kinds of questions from this
simulation even though it's very simple.
And now what is the action in this case?
I told you L I is the action integral of
the lrangian. And here in our simulation
we define all right. So the motion the
velocity of the ants will determine
their kinetic energy, right? The mass of
the ant times the velocity squared over
two. That's simple. And then the
potential energy is a little bit more
tricky. So here we model the potential
as effective potential coming from the
concentration of the pheromone that they
deposit. So that's equivalent of uh
information in in any other system.
Right? So the more information there is
the larger this potential and the faster
they will form the root. And here like
this exponent is just describing the
evaporation rate or if it's a brain it
will be the forgetting right the memory
loss or if it's some other system where
the information will deteriorate then
there is a diffusion term and this is um
a random term they they move with a
wiggle angle of they don't move always
on a straight line because they want to
explore the neighboring paths to see if
there is a shorter one. So in our run
they had plus - 25° at each step. They
don't just move along the the
information the steepest information
gradient the steepest uh concentration
gradient but they wiggle a little bit to
see well if there is a king here can I
find a shortcut can I make it even
shorter right so this helps them find
the lowest action path but obviously if
there is this random noise this makes
this analytically not solvable so the
simulation does solve it numerically
pretty much right and here is the output
from this simulation. So we have the
average action efficiency at the end
when they form the final trail not at
the intermediate stages. We have other
curves for that but this this will be
just the final state and here we change
the number of hands similar to the
number of cells in organisms or number
of people in society. And as you
increase the size of the system, again,
quantity quality transition, the more
ants you put in the simulation, the
larger you make that system in that
society,
the the shorter path they find, the more
efficient path they find. So, in other
words, in our language, it's better
organized, right? It obeys more closely
the the physics principles.
And uh
again like uh we saw a bunch of other
examples.
We also found uh something um very
interesting. So not only uh we call that
unit total dualism, right? So not oops
um let me go back
forward.
All right. So if we if we look at the
entropy the randomness of those um ants
in the simulation obviously at the
beginning they're the most random at the
end they have the least randomness the
least entropy but let's say the entropy
per the unit entropy and the final
entropy
for the same quantity entropy we also
find
power law relationships on a lo scale
this they scale they fall on a straight
line
and uh and we looked also the
information unit information total
information. So we think there is
something
even more important again as the size of
the system the total quantity of the
system is increasing. The total
u microscopic measures the microscopic
measures change proportionally as well.
And here is the average action
efficiency which will be like the
microscopic measure how each ant how
efficiently each ant is moving and the
the total amount of action again a power
low similar to the CPU or the stellar
evolution or any other of the data but
again what I mentioned earlier was that
um we don't want the variation of the
this average action to be
uh stationary to reach some final
minimum. But we want cosmic evolution.
We want those systems to keep getting
better and better and to transition to
more complex systems. So a dynamical
principle will be that this will not be
an equality anymore. the the variation
will not settle around some minimum
value but it will keep finding ways to
to shorten this uh to to to decrease the
action and here uh for broader audience
I'm uh kind of reminded now I'm just
tempted to say that uh you probably know
of Buckminister Fuller right he built
this geodeic dome in Canada in Montreal
for the Olympic games and Fuller is the
the bucky balls and named after him. But
he also came up with ephemeralization
which the definition is we'll do more
with less more with less until we could
do everything with nothing. So I think
this is exactly this equation. We'll do
more events with less action more events
with less action until we we could
pretty much do everything with almost
almost no expenditure. I don't know
whether that will happen and when it
will happen but I think it's a a tractor
state at least even if we don't reach it
I think that's kind of the the
teological goal of those systems to get
to this maximum efficiency until they
could do everything with nothing
and also here when I say about unit and
f unit and total quantities this dualism
I want to give this example with Javon's
paradox for those of you that are not uh
physicists But let's say this is an
economics paradox. Probably all of you
have heard it. It came from
I think long time ago maybe the 60s the
70s when there was the oil shock right
and people tried to make more efficient
cars because the fuel was very expensive
and they said well we'll save fuel if we
increase the efficiency of cars per mile
by a factor of two miles per gallon. uh
expenditure of fuel or the the run of
the cars, then we'll use half of the oil
in the world and everything will be
great. And when they build those more
efficient cars, what they found is that
the total amount of fuel expenditure
actually increased. And they were like,
what did they what just happened? We
doubled the efficiency of the cars. we
expected to half the the spending for
fuel and the fuel expenditure increased
even more and uh that's why he called it
paradox because they couldn't explain
it. Obviously the logical explanation is
as people pay less for per mile they'll
drive more miles and they'll do more
things right but in our language is as
you increase the efficiency of the
system the system could grow so you'll
increase the total action so this is I
think a feature not a bug it's a
necessary it's that's how complex
systems work that's how that's how they
selforganize it's not a paradox uh in
our understanding we think it's it's
necessary prerequisite for
self-organization
because they are in this positive
feedback loop so each of them increases
the other the efficiency increases the
total expenditure the total expenditure
increases the efficiency
and here I not going to spend much time
on this these are just sample
um like runs of the phase transition
from disorder to order of different
quantities It is like entropy, action
efficiency
information in terms of thermal and
density and average part time. And they
show this typical transition phase
transition behavior observed everywhere
in physics and in other systems.
Um this graph I showed you earlier just
to compare to remind you again of real
world systems displaying this unit total
dualism or size complexity rule. Uh so
the stars become more complex as they
get bigger. But also this is from one of
the Jeffrey West paper from uh um
like many like more than 15 years ago. I
think 2006 probably is the paper itself
where he looked at the log of the gross
metropolitan product of cities as a log
of the population of cities
and it's on a log scale. It's a power
law. It's hard to see here but um if you
look at the paper in the caption it's
like going at 1.15 the power in that
power law uh relationship. So as cities
are get bigger they are producing more
per person. So the unit productivity is
increasing as the total population of
the cities is increasing. So basically
there is no paradox. All right. So I
tried to bunch up bunch here everything
together to kind of summarize what I
talked. I hope it's not overwhelming but
a lot of these things we already talked
so it's kind of a review. So here I'm
repeating this least action principle.
It's also called Hamilton's principle
because he defined it in its modern
version where any particle or field in
physics will choose the least action
path the red line which is the straight
line if there are no other obstacles
versus all these other possibilities for
longer paths. And when we look at the
ant simulation they explore this longer
paths. They start with total randomness
but finally they choose the one that is
shortest with some because they have
this wiggle angle this random parameter.
It's a wider path. It's not a straight
line but still it's like the shortest
possible path that they would take the
most action efficient. And here I'm
repeating this feedback loop between the
action efficiency and the size or the
quantity and the quality of the system
which
pred which predicts this transition from
randomness to order
and I didn't even show here like the
exponential
transition and the power law scaling the
quantity quality transition or the size
complexity rule. Quantity quality is the
language of Hegel. size complexity the
language of Bonire
scaling of many people including Jeffrey
West but they all point to the same
thing because you increase the size of
the system it's complexity or quality is
increasing and also this unit total
dualism that the unit quantity is
proportional by a power law to the total
of the same quantity in the system and
we want to think of This principle to
minimize action and participating in the
positive feedback loop as the cause of
the self-organization
and this power law scalings and the
structure as the effect and we could
make a prediction beforehand solve these
equations and we looked at the outcome
in the data and we see correspondence.
So this is kind of a summary of all
these things and if I have a minute I
could this kind of the same thing
expanded a little bit more but again the
Hamilton's principle the shortest path
is the physically realized path in
nature the mechanism is this feedback
loops between here a lot more quantities
that we measured in our simulation and
this is the entropy change the phase
transition corresponding to the
different stages of an distribution
finding the structure which is the
shortest path at the end
and here I I I don't want to repeat many
of the graphs this kind of I already
mentioned some of them earlier but here
is one uh by carro he's anthrop he was
anthropologist and in ' 67 he published
a paper where he went to look at
indigenous tribes in the Amazon
rainforest. And he uh he went there
because he wanted them again like those
islands to be separated to form like a
separate society. And he looked at the
number of organizational traits that
they have a chieftain, a priest, a
tradesman, how many structures they have
in the society and on the x-axis is the
population.
And he observed that all these villages,
autonomous villages as he called them,
lay on this power law line. And he even
wrote that if one of them increased in
population and deviated let's say went
in this blank area here
this low is so strong that they either
have to form structures to get back to
the same power low line or if they don't
they will split in two and move back to
the line here. So they either will go up
in complexity or they'll go down in size
but they cannot stay away from this
power law proportionality.
So um here are some other relationship
between action efficiency and entropy
difference
uh also power total action and entropy.
We have huge amounts of graphs in the
paper from last year with the same title
as the talk. And um here is with
different populations. The entropy
starts with high entropy randomness and
scales down. And obviously even the
final state has more entropy for more
ants. But we looked at the entropy
change basically the randomness at the
beginning and at the end. And with
larger population they decrease larger
decrease in entropy which is uh the
reverse is increases in order as
measured by entropy
or you could say measure entropy is a
measure of um loss of information right
of uncertainty. So you could convert it
to information.
And to go back to the I told you I was
always thinking in terms of this cone
where oh some things are not showing
well where starting from the beginning
of self organization until today the
systems are growing in size
and they're growing up in in complexity
and in quality.
And that's what is forming this cone.
this reciprocality
between the size of the systems and and
their complexity going
uh up in this is an arrow of time of
increase of complexity
and um yeah in our model they grow
exponentially. So to finish I would say
to repeat that we understand at least
action principle as predicting the
increase of action efficiency because
the agents in any system should obey as
closely as they can the physics law the
physics principles move in the same way
as in any other system and that will
correspond to increase of structure
forming a more efficient or uh
organization in terms of action
efficiency,
but it's the average action efficiency
for all of them.
And then uh the system of this
interconnected characteristics
with positive feedback loops predicts
the exponential growth and power low
scalings which we saw in several
systems, several examples.
And this complexity size rule which is a
scaling relationship or power holds at
different levels of organization
physical like stellar, biological,
societal
in many systems.
And this unit uh total
dualism of these characteristics also
speaks about this connection between
kind of microscopic for a single agent
and microscopic for the whole system.
That system needs to get bigger for its
agents to get more efficient and the
agents need to get more efficient for
the system to grow bigger.
and also dynamic collection principles
because we have open-ended evolution and
it has to go in the words of um
uh Buckminister Fuller all the way to to
familialization or to in the physics
language maybe to zero action or close
asytoically to very very small action
per one event
and that we could predict that the most
action efficiency based on uh lap will
be the structure that are form
and uh
yeah so we think that action average
action efficiency provides this number
this measure. We could take two systems
and we say this system has organization
which corresponds to this number of
action average action efficiency and
this has a lower or higher number. So
it's less organized or more organized.
So we could quantify it and we think
that this
potential may have implications across
disciplines as people say if you cannot
measure something you cannot improve it.
So we need a a number a measure for how
organized a system instead of just
saying this looks more complex than the
others. And um with in future work we
think that this model could be extended
to different types of complex systems.
Let's say with modeling, with friction,
with dissipation, we could look at other
quantities
and also we could test it for more
specific like either biological or
social systems. Let's say can you model
a photosynthetic or crap cycle in
biology or metabolic cycles?
And also in technology, if nature uses
those optimization principles, how can
we use them to build more efficient
cities, more efficient
internet structures, communication
technologies, robotics, and so forth. So
I'll stop here. Thank you for your
attention.
And if you have any questions, I'll be
happy to talk more about this. Sorry if
I took too much time.
Okay, I did.
Thank you. Okay, great. Anyone watching
live can add a question in live chat.
Um, I guess just while I'm reccropping
everything, how did you come to this
question and what does research in your
lab look like for yourself and for
students?
Oh, how did I come to this question?
It's very interesting.
I could just tell you if you really want
to know. I was in high school and I'm
walking in my hometown. Okay, it's a
city but small city 200,000 people and
I'm looking I'm kind of imagining it
historically having this small
population this first houses and then
bigger buildings and bigger buildings
and I'm like all right if you go to New
York City you'll see this 100 story
skyscrapers so you have this increase of
density
and decre that means decrease of
distance between the points in the
system, right? To so not only you get
more efficient paths but the end points
are getting closer and closer. So that
even we didn't even talk about that you
increase the efficiency by shortening
the paths by getting the points closer
like in CPUs you make the uh kind of
transistor smaller and you decrease the
distance between them for the
computation that increases even more the
action efficiency. And I'm like, what is
going on? Where how does it go? I was
imagining maybe in the future the whole
city will fit in one building, which
which will be the ultimate efficiency.
Everything will be as close as possible.
It will take the least time to get from
here to there, which now if you look at
uh uh the Dubai buildings or some
others, they host pretty much whole
city. So I think may may have already
happened. Um and that could explain why
people why in the world people will
build such buildings. I I would in my
language that will be to decrease to
increase the interaction or to decrease
the time and and energy that it takes
for people to communicate or to get in
touch with each other. Obviously now we
have internet we can talk to anybody but
we still use physical kind of presence.
And then I started like uh I was reading
then at that time like uh the electrical
kind of philosophy and Hegel and I'm
like oh if the city is getting bigger
there is a quantity quality transition
it's getting more efficient people are
closer together they exchange more
information they create more inventions
they they build better structures right
and then I but there wasn't that I'm
talking about the 80s. Obviously, there
was the Santa Fe Institute, but it was
here and I was in Bulgaria and that was
behind the iron curtain. So, I couldn't
do anything in complexity or in this
kind of line of research. So I went to
study physics because I thought okay if
I uh if I want to explain why these
systems are self-organizing how they are
self-organizing probably I need to know
all these basic principles then I came
to the US to study I did my PhD at Tus
University in physics I did a postock at
northeastern in physics and then I went
teaching
and uh and even for my PhD and posdock
I couldn't
do anything in complex system. So I had
to do any other kind of physics that
will give me a PhD and and a pos and a
faculty position. And now after I got
those and I got tenure and promotion, I
could kind of
uh work full-time or think full-time
about those issues which gives me a
great pleasure now. So yeah, my question
always has been about why why is this?
What's going on?
What's this magic that's happening that
gives us this world instead of a
universe filled with hydrogen atoms
randomly dispersed everywhere or empty
space? Why in the world they built us?
How?
Yeah. So that's my motivation pretty
much.
Um yeah, very interesting. I really
appreciated the Buckminister Fuller
connection and it's very intriguing that
the path of least action follows a
geodessic in arbitrary state spaces
on kind of like a curved trajectory.
For example, the ant example, it wasn't
a straight straight line. it still had a
little wiggle that would be in tension
between the attractive uh character of
the pheromone and how much variability
and movement like all those different
features and so but yet across many
replicates of the simulation you would
get a straight line yet every single
line in practice is going to it's or
it's like it's like jumping rope. It's
like the average is flat, but that's
something that arises not necessarily
even at every collective behavioral
level. more like a across scenario
mean field or or central limit theorem
type results that gives an orderly
straight line through all the curves and
set up for that to be manifested in
geodessic architecture with tense segreg
to to it's very provocative Fuller
talked about people traveling more and
he said well people were into horse and
cart and then now there's the car the
car and then the plane and then what's
interesting is it goes up and up and up
but then it can't always and now average
travel for example might be I don't know
maybe it's dropping so
how do we reconcile
these smoothly fitting curves with
balancing knowing that like not
everything can curve in that regime
forever for
so what is it that switches regimes of
coherent scaling?
Well, thank you for that question. Yes,
I want to go back to my example that I
gave with the Boston Highway, the the
big dick as we call it here because it
was a big mess while they were doing it.
But uh I think that's why I kept
repeating that this is a first
approximation of this model. So this
smooth exponential and power law curves
uh if we look more carefully at data
um actually
I think they they have a sinosoidal kind
of looking like oscillation around the
exponential and I'll say what I mean
that when I said let's say what caused
people to build the new highway, the big
dick or the new infrastructure that will
increase the action efficient. Well,
that puts a population pressure. You got
more people, you got more congestion.
But that has a time delay. They can't
build it in real time, right? You get
five more people, you build another five
miles of highway or something, right?
So, you have to wait to uh some
threshold.
And I think um yeah the infrastructure
reaches some level and then it waits
until the pressure is large enough to
push it to the next level. So it it has
to almost in in this case with the
congestion it's almost like a a crisis
like you have this impossible way to
live and you have to do something but I
think there is this lack between all
those uh characteristics they don't just
smoothly as you said correctly and you
observed correctly they don't smoothly
incrementally increase each other and
grow proportional all the time
but I think they go in this uh multiple
logistics transitions right so they have
a transition to a new level and stop and
then wait until the rest of the system
grows to that level the rest of the
characteristics and then there is
another transition and it stops and this
way they build this and even Ray
Kerszswwell in his book the singularity
is near has exactly that figure or
similar figure at the beginning where he
has this sequential transitions between
different computational platforms right
let's say at the beginning people will
do calculations I don't know with abacus
for hundreds of years and then they'll
do with uh I don't know mechanical
calculators then with relay tubes but
between them there is kind of a a very
fast jump and then they stay they
plateau for a
So I think this is the real picture and
we're working how to put that in the
equation how exactly to reflected in the
model but that's you're very correct.
Yeah.
So I guess sort of in closing as we look
at on one hand the decades of systems
theory and multiscale complex systems
analysis agent based modeling etc that
brought us here and we look forward like
over the coming few years
what are you going to be looking for?
What do you feel like your own research
may yield? Are there events that you
anticipate that you feel would provide
important validation? Are there tool
developments or what will those advances
in tooling or development
provide?
Yes, thank you for that question. It's
very very probably the most important
question. Very spot on. So I'm asking
myself that every day.
Why the problem of self-organization and
order increasing in the universe hasn't
been solved so far 100 years ago. And I
think the main obstacle is that uh
non-equilibrium thermodynamics
hasn't been
uh fully developed and we need it in
order to understand what's happening in
systems away from thermodynamic
equilibrium. We know what happens in
thermodynamic equilibrium. Nothing.
Everything is the same. But the
interesting things happen away from
thermodynamic equilibrium. We don't have
a good theory for that. there are many
attempts
uh but what is giving me a great hope is
the following that
um and I think the reason that
non-equilibrium thermodynamics has not
been developed I'll sound now very
particular to my interest but I think I
have
uh hope that there is something true to
that is that the least action principle
itself which describes how all objects
move
has not also being uh used and extended
to its full power. And what I'm what I
mean by that is that um
most areas of physics people are
interested in just the conservative list
action principle which is kinetic minus
potential energy, no dissipation, no
randomness. Obviously the areas like
plasma physics, fluid dynamics where you
have those effects but recently there
have been enormous
there has been enormous progress in
including all the dissipation and and
randomness terms in list action
principle and um Andres um in 2017
provided a derivation of the maximum
entropy production principle. from the
this stoastic dissipatively section
principle which is a major that's the
the maximum entropy production is one of
the major debates because there are a
lot of people that point to different
exceptions but
for many people it's the main driver for
self-organization of systems but I think
actually we're working on that too uh
that uh maximum entropy production is a
consequence of this increased efficiency
and transport of energy through the
system and as the system becomes more
efficient it could absorb more energy.
Uh Jeremy England talked a lot about
that and it could dissipate dissipate
that energy faster and on top of that
the system grows as we saw in our model
with this uh interconnected
characteristics.
So I think that the maximum entropy
production yes it correlates with
increased
uh structure and uh complexity and
efficiency but I think it's the
byproduct kind of the exhaust of this
underlying
the the driving force is not the in
other words what I want to argue is the
system expels the entropy in the
environment.
So you could ask the question, what
benefit does the system have of this
expelled entropy? If anything, it it
raises the temperature of the
environment. It's detrimental, right?
But what the system benefits from is
absorbing more energy. So it could use
it to create better and more efficient
structures inside. And it also benefits
from minimizing the trajectories
and the friction along them to perform
its functions more efficiently with with
less energy expenditure and faster. And
I think these connections between the
expanded dissipative and stoastic list
action principle and its application to
non-equilibrium thermodynamics
and from there its application to
biological and social systems and
hopefully the brain. It's not there yet
but I see a lot of papers recently
defining and working. I've seen least
action
principles defined for neural networks,
for for AI, for all kinds of systems.
And I think people are converging on
this opinion that we need to look at at
something objective that is the systems
are having a goal to to get to this most
efficient state. They're not just
randomly exploring the space. They're
they're moving in a direction. So, so my
hope is that by uh developing this
theory collectively many people from
many different areas to have a coherent
theory of self-organization in all of
these systems and also to add that I
think a lot of things have been
rediscovered in a lot of areas. I
mentioned optimal control theory. Yeah,
it's based on the least action
principle. It's used in economics and in
social systems. It's optimizing for
different characteristics that I
mentioned in the model.
But um very few people in in physics are
interested in it because they say oh
weed in atoms, molecules like fields and
all these other systems there somebody
else should deal with them. And at the
same time a lot of the biologist and
people they are extremely smart people
but but we are limited in our brain
capacity. We can be experts in every
field. We I I'm not an expert in
chemistry and in biology. So somebody in
other field will may not be expert in
physics. So it's hard to make this
interdisiplinary connections. We talked
a little bit earlier about this empty
area between the disciplines between
because we are so specialized in our own
areas and and we have very limited brain
capacity to become absolute expert in
that next area and make that connection
right and that's why there is so much in
between that we we we haven't explored
yet and I think that's where the answers
are that's why I'm interested in in this
fields. Yeah, lot lot of interesting
pieces there. What does the environment
as we see order emerge? You know, as we
see a crystal precipitate out of a
solution,
it's easy to say how the crystal changes
and grows and scales. But what does the
surrounding get? Is it getting
is it taking the loss and it is getting
disordered or does it become more
ordered as well
because its topological
or dynamic properties also become richer
through
um re-entry of interactions with
increasingly sophisticated systems like
ants modifying the environment. That's a
key piece. You get certain meanfield
behavior and central limit theorem
behavior from flocks of birds.
However, you get another broader
category with pheromone and niche
modification because the special case of
niche modification is just not doing it.
At which point it's more like a
transient process rather than something
that has this historical element. And so
certainly the dynamics of life on earth
have been shaped by oxygenation events
and by changes and all these different
things as well. So the question of
whether the environment
is sort of like soaking up
or possibly even it's like a double
downhill and they're both coming to
game.
I think yeah this is spot on. Yeah,
that's the most important question. This
is I guess at the heart of the active
inference, right? How the system
reflects and how closely reflects its
surroundings and how internal structure
kind of corresponds
to that environment. And I think yes,
they grow in tandem.
they become more complex because even in
an ecosystem,
right? Every time let's let's imagine
one species has a mutation that makes
its metabolic cycle twice as efficient
to produce ATP than another species.
Obviously, they'll outco compete them
because they need half of the food to do
the same things, right?
And if there is drought they will
survive but that will change the whole
ecosystem. So now all the other species
will see a different environment.
Obviously that will create this entropy
mismatch between the prediction what
they know the system is but it changed
meanwhile. So they need to adapt to the
changes and in this adapt uh adaptivity
to adapt they have to change their own
internal structure right so the the
inter I talked only yes I talked only
about the internal structure in this
simulation and how
what's happening inside the system to to
function
but it's paramount to not forget that
all that happens in the system is based
on what's happening in the environment
outside of the system. Right? If there
is if you stop the energy inflow
uh the system the the interior will
disintegrate. Right? So it has to find
the energy from somewhere and um
information plays absolutely crucial
role. In fact action in living systems
at least cannot be minimized without
information. Let's say if you think
about the simplest of the simple let's
say a simple bacterium right so it will
move it will have sensors for light or
for a chemical which is food but what is
the sensing of light mean well it means
it has information where the sun is so
it needs to let's say photosynthesize
and then it has so if it did not have
that sensor and it has to find where
there is more sunlight It pretty much
has to move randomly like the ants at
the beginning of the simulation, but
that's the maximum action path. So, it
will spend all of its energy before it
finds its food. So, it will die. But
knowing where the food is, the the end
point, it could move more or less on a
straight line, maybe like the ants with
a little wiggle, but it will get to the
food the fastest way. And maybe if you
have two different bacteria and one is
more sensitive to light and it moves on
a shorter line, it will get there first
and it will out compete the other. So I
think the information is the mechanism
through which organisms could find the
shortest action path. Yeah, there's a
lot I could add. I think part of the
mystery there is let's just say the
first bacteria to get there died or it
modifies it so that a second bacteria
can come something like that. Yeah. So
then there's some fitness function
geodessic path of least action that may
or may not have
a sort of monotonic relationship with
any given phenotype.
So how to understand the phenotype
distribution
as taking a path but not necessarily
doing what it first at first glance
appears to be doing. Like for example
like you you mentioned enzymes
efficiencies. So that's like the futile
cycle. It's like why are there enzymes
that are both phosphorolating and
defosphorilating? I'm like isn't that a
waste? And it's like, well, yes, if you
never had to switch gears, it would be
wasteful. But if you need to have some
agility, then you want to have both
lanes going, even if you pay a small
cost to keep both of the directions
open.
So then it's like again there's some
fitness maximizing strategy that doesn't
necessarily involve what appears to be
maximum efficiency on enzyme synthesis.
But it's like yet we know what's here
must reflect some
draw
from that space of paths.
But it might be a very curvy line itself
relative to that imaginary straight
line.
And that line might not be doing what we
think it's doing. But we can hypothesize
that it is there and that discovering it
or inferring it would give us deeper
insight than merely describing using
descriptive statistics.
I agree with you that uh well I would go
to the Ashb's law of uh requisite
variety right that's uh the variet the
internal the way I understand it is the
internal structure of the system has to
reflect the variety of the environment
to have a chance to survive right or to
to match that complexity
uh But in your question, the way I
understand your question is it sounds
like a redundancy, right? You have some
you have two processes for like um that
that in some situation one could be
turned on in another situation a
different could be turned on, right?
And uh I I see that. So that's that's
the next level of theory, right? You
could say, well, I mean, yes, you're
right. This system is not doing just one
thing, but today it could be in one
environment, tomorrow it could be in
another environment, right? So, um,
let's say in the summer it's hot here.
You need one kind of clothes, in the
winter it's cold. So, you can't have one
optimization function for for all of
them. So, you have to match.
But in all of these cases, let's say the
environment changed and now you have to
switch gears to this other mechanism. I
don't know if it corresponds I'm not a
biologist but I know that gene
expression like the
uh is the the way that like you have all
the information in the DNA but at any
given moment you need small part of it
and you turn only this gene only that
gene depending on what the organism
needs at that time. So I think this
this provides this uh flexibility when
the environment changes for that
organism to be able to do
I hope the best or the most efficient
thing for that new situation
keeping the other mechanism just in case
when it goes back to the previous one so
there is some memory effect it knows
that
things will change. Yeah, I guess to
sort of close with another Buckminister
Fuller quote, he said, "All known cases
of extinction are due to
specialization."
And it's sort of like, yeah, even if the
bacteria is at 97°
and it's adapted there forever and then
the niche changes to 92, well, either it
has the plasticity at the individual or
the population level to adapt or it was
specialized to 97, then it went extinct.
So, it's kind of like right there is
that trade-off because you do better and
better more efficiently, but then you
become a specialist, you become 10ear
track 97° thermal bacteria
and it becomes hard to pivot and then
fitness is
decreased and the system becomes fragile
again.
Yeah, I think the next level you ask me
the first question about the extension
of this theory or many other approach
will be to let's say here I always say
this is very simple like two nodes very
simple case very first order
approximation
uh I'm looking because we haven't
described it so far and I'm trying to
see how this principle could apply to
the simplest case of minimization of one
process
for action let's say but when the system
let's say over the the year there may be
or over the day 100 changes in the
environment right let's say a bacterium
could sit in a pond and there could be
sunlight then there could be some
chemical coming then there could be
another chemical then there could be
some perturbation that there could be
heat wave and if it you said was just a
second ago if it cannot respond on 20 of
those it will die. So what will be the
overall efficiency? This will be another
super kind of efficiency for all of
these different processes. Right? So in
other words,
if the system cannot respond to one of
these, let's say some chemical change,
it means that when the input comes, it
it cannot efficiently process it or turn
it into something useful. I don't know
how to describe it because it's like in
biological terms. But uh that will be an
inefficiency in my understanding that it
will kill the system because it will
spend huge amounts of time and energy to
defend itself. But it cannot find the
the shortest way and it moves around and
around and around and it exhausts all of
its energy and dies. But it has to be
able to survive. It has to be able to do
this in all these different situations
and instances.
And obviously organisms die. They they
can't always adapt to they are not
always prepared for whole situations.
There have been millions of extinction
events. Many many species are not
adapted to the human activity today. So
yes, one one inefficiency will be one
inefficiency in one aspect maybe is a
good way to put it. It's enough to kill
the organism for that time frame that it
happens. And that's very unfortunate.
Yes, most ant species are extinct. The
ones are here, they're awesome, but most
of them are extinct. Um, yeah, they they
have probably learned to respond to huge
variety of changes in the environment
and survive,
be robust. That's a question about
robustness, resilience and yeah
redundancy in the system to ensure that
yeah a lot more layers on top of this
theory that I talked about. Cool. Well,
thank you again for the presentation.
Hope to hear updates on the research and
and from your group. So, thank you very
much.
Well, thanks Daniel and hopefully I will
have a chance to talk again in the
future and I'll update you if I have
something new. Awesome.
Bye-bye.